Finding Aid for the Otis Ferguson Papers PASC.0260
UCLA Library Special Collections
Otis Ferguson papers
1931-1986
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ferguson, Otis
PASC.0260
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Collection consists of scrapbooks, letters and ephemera related to the career of film critic Otis Ferguson.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Audio and audiovisual materials in this collection are restricted and require advance notice for use.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID:9948573783606533
Biography
Otis Ferguson was born in Worcester, MA, Aug. 14, 1907. At the age of 17, Ferguson joined the Navy and served four years. After graduating from Clark University in 1933, where he was senior class poet and editor of the yearbook, Ferguson was hired at The New Republic. There he reviewed books, films, and sometimes theater and eventually became an assistant editor. In 1936 Ferguson started writing about music, particularly big swing bands and loaned his title to Dorothy Bakers novel, Young man with a Horn. He was later sent to Hollywood to write a series of articles about films and is best remembered as a film critic. Soon after Pearl Harbor, Ferguson joined the Merchant Marines and was killed during the war, ca. 1943.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of scrapbooks, letters and ephemera related to the career of film critic Otis Ferguson. Also includes notes and correspondence related to Dorothy Chamberlain. The collection may have been assembled by Dorothy Chamberlain after Ferguson's death for her book project, The Otis Ferguson Reader, circa 1982.
Organization and Arrangement
There is no specific arrangement to the collection.
Film critics -- Archives.; Chamberlain, Dorothy; Ferguson, Otis, 1907-1943--Archives.
- Book Contracts and list of people who contacted Ferguson about possible book, ca. 1934, 1938, 1941 (Box 1)
- Convoy [PQ18], ca 1942-43 (Box 1)
- Copyright Renewals, ca. 1966-1972 (Box 1)
- Correspondence (folder 1of 2), ca. 1934-1941 (Box 1)
  General note
  Including but not limited to: Philip Dunne, Hamilton Basso, Jimmy Durante, Alfred Hitcock.
- Correspondence (folder 2 of 2), ca.1936-1941 (Box 1)
  Including but not limited to Paul Jarrico, Nunally Johnson, Garon Kanin, Fritz Lang, Gene Lockhart, William McFee, Carey McWilliams, H.L. Mencken, John Jacob Niles, Clifford Odets, William Saroyan, and Stark Young.
- Dorothy Chamberlains rights and letters of transferal, ca. 1940s-1980s (Box 1)
- Film Criticisms of Otis Ferguson, Reviews, etc. - scrapbook, 1935-1982 (Box 3)
  Scrapbook of clippings.
- Jazz Rhythm, ca. 1938-40 (Box 1)
  Original manuscripts and copies of writings by Ferguson.
- Negatives (6 items), no date (Box 1)
  5 negatives for photogpaphs found in the folder labeled Photographs.
- Otis Correspondence, etc., 1934, 1980s (Box 1)
  Dorothy Chamberlins file regarding Ferguson.
- Otis Fergueson articles in books; Tributes to Ferguson, 1931-1943, 1964 (Box 3)
  Articles by and tributes to Ferguson.
- Otis Fergueson Miscellaneous -scrapbook, 1934-1945 (Box 3)
  Articles by Ferguson. New Republic "Correspondence" and "Mailbag" Colum; clippings about Salerno and PQ-18.
- Otis Fergueson Movies - scrapbook, 1934-1941 (Box 3)
  Articles by Ferguson.
- Otis Ferguson Books and Writers I - scrapbook, ca. 1933-1937 (Box 2)
  Aticles by Ferguson (1933 - 9 June 1937).
- Otis Ferguson Books and Writers II - scrapbook, ca. 1937-1940 (Box 2)
  Articles by Ferguson (30 June 1937 -8 April 1940).
- Otis Ferguson Books and Writers III - scrapbook, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  Articles by Ferguson (15 April 1940 - 25 August 1941).
- Otis Ferguson Books and Writers IV - scrapbook, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  Articles by Ferguson (1 September 1941 - 2 March 1942).
- Otis Ferguson Music and Theater - scrapbook, 1938-1941 (Box 2)
  Articles by Ferguson; mostly cut outs from The New Republic.
- Otis Ferguson Reader: Articles, Reviews I - scrapbook, ca. 1982 (Box 2)
  Original and photocopied clippings and articles.
- Otis Ferguson Reader: reprints of writing, ca. 1980s (Box 1)
  Lists.
- Otis Ferguson Reader: Reviews II - scrapbook, ca. 1983-1985 (Box 2)
  Letters, copied clippings and articles.
- Phonographs donated from Ferguson Estate, ca. 1973 (Box 1)
  Restricted:
- Photographs (25 items), ca. 1910-1940 (Box 1)
  Negatives for 5 of the photographs found in folder labeled Negatives.
- Portrait of An American Tragedy, no date (Box 3)
  Portrait of an American by Robert Coffin personalized by Ferguson with pictures and captions.
- Vanity Fair, 1986 May (Box 3)
  Ferguson mentioned on page 40.